So this is in terms of uh
selfmortification. >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> It's one of the extreme domains that the
Buddha said one shouldn't go into. And
the other one is sensuality. M
>> so
usually when a person hears that craving
in terms of sensual activity is bad the
mind or that person swings to the
opposite extreme of self- torture
thinking that self torture is now the
that's what I should do
>> the belief that punishing the body will
purify the mind
>> or you know if I just punish myself
>> then feel pain now then everything that
I've done bad in the past all these
afflictions my suffering will end I will
burn away all the past kind of
consequences of consequences of my bad
actions >> and end the suffering once and for all
>> and end the suffering once and for all
>> so you know the classic one would be
sitting for long hours
trying not to move staring at something
until >> you know it's painful but you just
>> you know it's painful but you just
endure it
>> don't feel the hunger,
>> you know, uh don't don't speak,
>> don't see anything. It's just just
shutting trying to shut everything down.
>> And so the Buddha says that this is not
uh I'll just actually read the
definition. These two domains should not be gone to
These two domains should not be gone to
by one who has gone forth. The pursuit
of happiness, insensual pleasures, the
pursuit of self-mortification,
both of which are ignoble and
unbeneficial. Without going to these
domains, the tatagata has awakened to
the middle way which give rise gives
rise to peace, enlightenment.
So this self-mortification that's a it
is a common
reaction to giving up sensuality or
trying to give up sensuality sensual
activity. >> How do we know that we are actually not
>> How do we know that we are actually not
going into that domain and actually
because giving up sensual activity is
painful. So that seems like selfmodification.
So that seems like selfmodification.
Maybe I should just give into sensuality
a little bit.
>> Well, yeah. I think that's the
so a certain amount of information and
knowledge and learning
needs to take place because um yeah, I
remember I heard people say that before
that basically restraining like being
celibate is a form of selfmotification
because you have to endure your desires
therefore you're torturing yourself
therefore that's a wrong way. M
>> um
>> so then the alternative to that is then
sensuality for that person.
for that person.
>> Yeah.
>> Because so they don't see anything in
the middle. So yes, it might feel like
selfmotification initially when you say
no to to your desires and take on
training in the precepts.
Um but you have to go through certain
amount of withdrawal
like if you were dependent on on certain
types of drugs and so on uh uh not
taking them anymore will hurt for a bit.
How long? Well, it depends how dependent
you were. Uh and then uh and then you
would you would uh well you wouldn't
you would cease to suffer on account of
um withdrawal from those same things.
Um so how to differentiate mortification
versus essential indulgence? Well, take
on the precepts
and don't take on any other observances
that have nothing that that are not
mentioned in the precepts.
It's just what going to happen is
uh a mind of doubt. It's going to start
besetting you because you take on the
precepts. You develop sense of a container and so
You develop sense of a container and so
on. But then yeah, sensuality would come
back. Desires would be prompted by
sight, sounds, melt, touches, by this or
that. And that would be painful
obviously because you blocked the only
outlet that you knew which was acting
out of it sensuality.
But you don't want to stay with that
pain. You want to get rid of it.
And the only ways of getting rid of it
is either give back to into sensuality
and engage with it again or perhaps try
and get rid of the whole thing which is
which is always practically manifested
through oh let me introduce more things
that I won't do more observances
more tightening so that this uh state of
mind that bothers me affected with
desire and doubt so it doesn't come up
at all.
So that's how people fall into
selfmortification and observances and um
being bound by silabata paramasa. It's
because the pains of desires and
hindrances that are revealed through uh
training in the precepts and sense
restraint they don't want to bear them.
They don't want to stay with them. They
want to get rid of them.
And as I said since the only way of
getting rid of them before was giving
into them. Now you stop doing that. So
now the only way to get rid of it is
okay let me do more of other things that
will then prevent this from arising in
the first place
[snorts] and that's why you end up like
adding observances adding the duty
all because you don't want to stay with
the mind states that were revealed
through keeping the precepts but that's
really what training in the precepts
mean staying with the mind states that
are revealed through keeping the
precepts that's how you start to train in them.
They're not meant to shelter you from
those mind states. They're meant to
simply not make it worse, not allow the
mind to escape you towards sense objects
in the way it used to when you started
acting out and so on. But
once the mind is contained, once the the
pressures, the desires, the cravings are
contained through the prism, they're
going to feel unpleasant, of course. And
that's the training now. staying with
that, not trying to introduce more
rules, more techniques so that it
doesn't come up at all.
>> It's like no, no, no. You want it to
come up. It will come up whether you
want it or not.
>> You don't want to run away from it. You
don't want to try to get rid of it. You
don't want to act out of it. You want to
learn how to become immovable in face of
it while it's there. That's how then you
will truly not be touched.
So, so if a person [clears throat]
person suffering, they either try to get
rid of that suffering through sensual
activity. >> Well, yeah. Yeah. You give into
>> Well, yeah. Yeah. You give into
sensuality to get rid of the pain of the
desire. >> Like if the desire were not unpleasant,
>> Like if the desire were not unpleasant,
you would have absolutely it would be
inconceivable to seek the sense objects
and proliferate and engage with with
bodily pleasures. It will be
inconceivable. But because desire is
unpleasant, that's why you head in that
direction as a default.
>> And then
>> so you stop doing that.
>> Stop doing that. And then you still act
out in another way which is kind of try
to you okay self torture. Well, yeah,
you have the extreme examples or I'll
just try and destroy the senses so that
then these mind states that I have to
endure, I don't have to endure
>> or crush it kind of.
>> Exactly. So, if you if you if somebody
doesn't go that um in that course manner
try to destroy the senses or starve them
out or something, they would still then
oh let me do more things so that u
senses will not come across anything
that can provoke the mind. All of that
is just as I said kind of initially you
will have you will be doing that to some
extent you need to protect your senses
that's the purpose of the sense
restraint but how far you start taking
that is going to determine whether you
are now crossing into the the domain of
selfmotification i.e
just trying to manage the senses so that
the mind states don't come up because
you don't want to have to endure them
and deal with them. And that's the
fundamental difference.
[clears throat] It's like a person can
um
choose to restrain
their sight, what they look at and so
on. But inevitably things will come
within a range. You'll see it and the
mind will be provoked. The provoked mind
is unpleasant. feels unpleasant. You
don't want to state with you don't want
to stay with that particular type of
discomfort, the state of mind. So
instead, you know, well, like the sa
says, let me um those are the let me not
see the sights like a blind man. In
other words, let me pull my eyes out.
It's like, well, you'll stop seeing the
sights, but the mind remained equally
untrained. And now you even lost one of
the means of accessing that untrained
mind, revealing that untrained mind.
Mhm. >> So it's important that you have to
>> So it's important that you have to
recogn what what you have to recognize
is that you it's important to not act
out of the intention towards sights but
at the same time not to try and destroy
the eyes because you want the
non-intentional sights to provoke your
mind. That's what the training will be
when you have no intention to look,
smell, taste, touch towards any sensual
object yet they come in the range and
yet the wild animal is provoked
and it's like oh that's why I didn't do
this. This is the nature of the senses
and the untrained mind.
So that's the difference that uh
training in the virtue will reveal how
your intention matters whether the
provocation came on account of you
intentionally provoking it intentionally
looking intentionally tasting touching
smelling and so on or unintentionally.
So first you have to completely abandon
the intentional provocation, intentional
adding of the fuel so that then you can
discern the unintentional
um
kind of the unintentional environment so
to speak that then your mind reacts to
and then that's where the training
that's where the communication can can
occur. So but again if you don't know
that you would then think that's a
problem as well because it hurts because
it's unpleasant because desire pressure
is still there.
And it's and because of that you want to
get rid of that as well. So let me then
go on top of a mountain, pull my eyes
out, block my ears, never see, smell,
taste, touch, and I'll be safe. It's
like no, you're just going to destroy
the means of revealing the untrained
mind, the five senses, and yet the mind
will remain equally trained.
>> Or let me focus hard on some
concentration technique where I'll stop
perceiving any senses, anything that
comes and that's the peace. No, that's
just shutting down. The peace is when no
amount of sight, sound, smell, taste,
touches, unintentional or intentional
for that matter, can provoke the mind
towards desire, ill will, or
distraction. But in order to get to that point, first
But in order to get to that point, first
you have to stop doing all the
intentional acts towards those unh
wholesome things in order to reveal the
unintentional provocations on account of
the wild mind in order to calm that
down. When [clears throat] the mind is
fully cal trained properly understood
then intention or unintent it's all
pured anyway. It's all purified anyway.
[snorts]
>> So it's self-mortification is aversion
basically like
>> yeah you know it's
>> yeah exactly
>> uh towards what you're experiencing. So
and there is a suta where the Buddhist
says that uh you know as a bodhic sattva
as he was beginning to train he thought
pleasure is not to be reached through
pleasure. So
um freedom
>> from duka is not to be reached through
pleasure. >> Pleasure is to be reached through pain.
>> Pleasure is to be reached through pain.
That's what he thought. Like if I just
>> if I just inflict the pain
>> Yeah.
>> then eventually it would get to this
nibbana. >> But it depends what type of pain we're
>> But it depends what type of pain we're
talking about. That's the point.
>> Yeah.
You can have a pain of of just bearing
the elements, bearing the discomfort,
uh bearing the power of your
determination, sticking to it, and that
will not necessarily result in anything,
anything of value. But you have a that,
as I said, particular type of pain
that's not terribly unpleasant,
you know,
>> particular type of pain,
>> particular type of pain. pain of the
recognition of the untrained mind from
within that you are containing but not
trying to kill or suffocate either. M
>> so it's like the the the pain of of of
that of that mind of that pressure and
then another pain that comes on top of
it is the recognition of oh this needs
to be tamed where do I even begin
and like the doubt now the pain of doubt
the pain of not knowing whether it works
whether or not where does sensor stren
all of that it's a lot harder to stick
to in terms as a training and practice
then oh just tell me a technique that I
will mindlessly adhere to literally I
won't have to think about anything else
that there's a reason these techniques
are popular and are mainstream because
again they feed into that very thing of
okay so if I just adhere to this
mechanical precepts repetition doing
this or that I don't have to feel the
the life of this wild animal
>> I can just keep as it comes up I can
just is putting new things on top of it
more and more and with a hope that
eventually it will stop coming up.
>> Yeah. So the measure the longer I do it
the harder I do it it's going to work
>> the stiffer it is the the more rigid it
is. Yeah.
So the and yeah so it means pain
purification comes through
>> well patient endurance that can't
patience endurance of what
>> not of anything that that you think of
or feel dutiful towards patient
endurance of the states of the mind that
come up as a result of you imposing
virtue and sense restraint as a form of
training.
So when see you could say there is a
desire to look or taste something and
then you said no to yourself because it
was against the precepts
and then maybe it wasn't against the
precepts but it was clearly rooted in
sensuality. Um say you wanted to eat
something that was unnecessary and you
wanted to increase you want to start
practicing sense restraint and you said
no to it and now that desire the mind of
that desire it's going to rebel. It's
going to it's going to complain about
it. It's going to try and attack you.
It's going to try and get you back under
its will.
So that's not pleasant. It's just from
inside. It's like you're being being basically
It's like you're being being basically
threatened from inside.
So the right training means staying with
that, not acting out of it, but not
trying to get rid of it. However, as I
said, it's a it's unpleasant. It's
unpleasant in a very specific kind. A
specific kind that nobody will
accidentally choose to adopt. Nobody
will accidentally choose to stay with
that particular level of of discomfort
that your own mind threatens you and so
on with.
>> So instead it's a lot easier then say
you said no to this desire. Now there's
the mind of desire comes up. or let me
now focus on my breathing or do this
technique or watch my sensations or in
other words let me distract myself with
anything else now all the other things
that are on paper said as wholesome so
that this mind goes away
and then it might work and it might work
once twice it might work 10 times but
you always have to do it whenever the
mind comes you always have to calm it
down because you don't know how to deal
with it and the problem is not that um
oh I want to calm the mind. So the
problem is that you basically believing
that you need to act
and and and suppress the mind states
that are revealed on account of
restraint and virtue
carries the implicit view that will then
prevent you from uprooting it. In other
words, prevent you from actually
addressing the problem. So that the mind
will mind in itself will stop having the
desire to pressure you with.
Because if there is if the mind itself
has lost the desire towards things you
said no to, that's the true calming.
>> That's the true non-disturbance.
Oh, the animal is not reactive anymore.
It does not attack anymore. I don't need
to
practice keeping the leash and and
restraining it and suffocating it and
holding it down. Like the virtue did
that for you. Basically, it revealed the
state of how deeply the animal was
untrained, how wild it was. But now, do
you do more things so you don't have to
do that work of training it? Or do you
recognize that the real training is
okay, the mind of desire is present.
Okay, the wild animal is here. um if I
try to run away from it, act out of it,
none of that will result in
communicating the right things to it. So
first and foremost, I have to
acknowledge that that's the state of
mind for what it is and stay with it,
know it as such.
>> That's why in that other suta when
somebody asked the Buddha, you know,
Master Goautma said the dharma is
directly visible here and now. How
should that be understood?
And people would, you know, often think
how the direct visible, the here and
now, the the the present moment
awareness, all sorts of mystical ideas
about it. And the Buddha didn't didn't
answer any of that in that manner. He
said, well, when you know the mind of
lust as mind of lust, a mind of aversion
as mind of aversion, that's how dharma
is directly visible.
>> Yeah. Not because you know I can
contemplate the for noble truth and the
edful path and patitimada or as I say go
in the mystical direction and just start
um describing it in some who knows
idiosyncratic terms. No no no no
recognizing the mind for what it is as
it is such staying with it is how you
practice the dharma. How you get to see
the dharma directly visible here and now
>> for see the for everything else follows
from it.
So the recognition of the mind states
that come as a result of the
uh restraint, virtue and so on. That's
how you get to practice the dharma.
[snorts] That's how you get to see it.
Okay? That's how you get to see the
principle uh behind that whole training
that we describe.
So the selfmortification would always as
I said would always kind of it could
have these obviously coarse extremes but
it actually goes as far as
>> you have a mind state that has a reason
you don't want it. You're aversive
towards it. I I want to get rid of this
mind because it hurts me and that's why
I hate it.
>> So that's the beginning.
>> So you're acting out of aversion now.
>> First you want to act out of sensual
desire. You said no to that. Now there
is a painful mind. Now you want to get
rid of that. That's just like, oh, so
now you're going to the aversion
direction. So just wanting to get rid of
that, adopting sets of behaviors, rules,
duties, techniques to get rid of it, to
keep the lid on it, to keep it down so
you don't have to deal with it. That's
already a form of selfmotification
because you believe that by adhering to
a certain u technique or just mindless
adherence to the duty or what a says and
I don't have to think about I'll just do
it, I'll just do it, I'll just do it
that will free my mind from this wild
tendencies. It's like no
>> you can and you can keep the lid
forcefully for decades if you want. The
day will come when you forget about the
lid when you won't close it properly for
one reason or the other and the same
wild animal is going to come out and
because nothing has changed in terms of
its internal tendencies. And that's the
deer herd suta that we mentioned so many
times. It's like, no, they shun the
bait. They shun the pressure of the
bait, the proximity of the bait, and run
into the mountains. Now they're safe
there. And then they run out of food
there, and they come back because they
have to eat sooner or later. They come
back, and they still didn't learn how to
differentiate the bait and not act
towards the bait, and they get again
hooked, caught, and then Mara does with
them what he wants.
>> Yeah.
But the fact that you have to keep a lid
on things means and you're running away.
that that whole state means that you're
running away from something. There's
something you're keeping a lid on that
hasn't changed at all.
>> Yeah. If you keep the lid on things
because you recognize, well, I need to
keep the lid on things for now, but you
don't confuse that for the actual
training of that which is underneath the
lid. >> Yeah. Trying to cover.
>> Yeah. Trying to cover.
>> Yeah, you will be keeping the lid on
things one way or the other. But what
I'm talking about here is now when you
develop a view that keeping the lid on
the wild mind is something that will
magically just result in that mind not
being wild anymore eventually. [snorts]
So yeah, so uh the
one suffers and then you get you just
you you choose the path of punishing
yourself >> like if I feel that I punish myself then
>> like if I feel that I punish myself then
things will be okay in some sense. I
just so a classic example would be like
uh I break the precepts. I try and keep
the pre I break the precepts whatever I
uh
I lied to someone or whatever sexual
activity >> whatever
>> whatever
>> you feel guilty on that so you then
determine well
that guilt is you know suffering and I
shouldn't do that and that was wrong
thus I will not eat for next 10 days
next 10 days I'm not going to eat I'm
not going to look at
>> purify myself yeah
>> so you're trying to make this
>> that's apples and oranges basically like
nothing to do with one another.
>> Yeah.
>> So, just just to say there it's kind of
trying to make a deal like you you
determining what the price is.
>> Yeah.
>> For the to what
>> and then making a deal with yourself.
>> Yeah.
>> Oh, yeah. That's a good deal. Oh, thank
you. [laughter] That
>> I can do that, you know.
>> And then you you start doing that just
the more pain you feel for not eating
[clears throat] you. You think that this
is paying for what I've done.
>> Yeah. I'm paying. Yeah. This is
>> But who are you to
>> who are you to decide the price? Yeah.
Exactly. you're in no position because
you're the one that owes the money.
So the point is you break the precepts,
you fail, you acknowledge that to that
extent, you confess it. Guilt comes up,
you don't try to get rid of the guilt.
If it comes up on account of like
rational guilt,
if it comes up on account of you
factually breaking the precepts, well,
let it sink in.
Sure. If the mind starts revolving
around it irrationally, well, you
recognize that, you still don't try to
get rid of it. You just restrain your
mental input towards the irrational
guilt. You don't try to get rid of the
state of mind
and that's how you learn from it. That's
how the Buddha would say like yes um
transgressing and then confessing it,
recognizing your fault to that extent is
how you grow in this training.
>> [clears throat]
>> not beating yourself up.
>> Yeah. Or like not confessing and then
just uh doing some random things as a
penance. >> It's like well you know where where the
>> It's like well you know where where the
penance is,
bringing it out to the light,
acknowledging it.
>> Yeah. And it's like if I if I act out of
lust, well, the only
way that I'm going to
really pay for it, so to speak,
>> and overcome the consequences of all my
lustful actions.
>> To me, the only thing that you would do
is to uprove the lust, of course,
>> forever. So you never do it again.
>> Yeah.
>> That would mean that you are
>> truly rehabilitated.
>> Rehabilitated. Yeah. Yeah.
>> You are. That's like the confession. You
know, I I acted out I lust because I
I want want to act out last
>> and I still maintain that lust.
>> Uh but if I'm really sorry then I should
give up lust for
>> and that's where the the the the actual
purity comes from the purity of the mind
when you're actually uprooting the lust
not just adhering to the traditional
observances and so on
like oh you know I never break the
precepts I'm pure. It's like, well, you
never break the precepts means you're
not making things worse, but you're far
from pure.
>> Like precepts prevent you from adding,
as we said before,
adding fuel to that fire, but they do
not they do not approve the problem in
and of themselves. You have to make the
effort and tame that animal
[snorts] like fully approve and and and
extinguish those desires of that
untrained wild mind and all those tendencies that
wild mind and all those tendencies that
he has by containing it by staying with
it by seeing through it
by by by presenting it with right
perceptions at the right time. All the
other like higher modes of training that
would have talked about
>> discerning a nature
>> discerning a nature unattractiveness
loving kindness all those things that
you would be bringing to the mind
depending on its state in order you for
you to to to communicate to it to teach